This is Pleurobot.
هذا بلوروبوت.
Pleurobot is a robot that we designed to closely mimic a salamander species
إنه ربوت صُمم ليحاكي نوع من السمندل
called Pleurodeles waltl.
يسمى (بلورديلز والت).
Pleurobot can walk, as you can see here,
كما ترون هنا، بليوروبوت يستطيع المشي،
and as you'll see later, it can also swim.
و سترون لاحقًا، أنه يستطيع السباحة أيضًا.
So you might ask, why did we design this robot?
ربما تتساءلون لماذا صممنا هذا الروبوت؟
And in fact, this robot has been designed as a scientific tool for neuroscience.
في الحقيقة تم تصميم هذا الربوت ليكون أداة تُستخدم في علم الأعصاب.
Indeed, we designed it together with neurobiologists
وبالطبع، قمنا بتصميمه بمساعدة علماء الأعصاب
to understand how animals move,
لنفهم كيف تتحرك الحيوانات،
and especially how the spinal cord controls locomotion.
بالأخص كيف يتحكم النخاع الشوكي في الحركة.
But the more I work in biorobotics,
وكلما تعمقت في الروبوتات الحيوية،
the more I'm really impressed by animal locomotion.
انبهرت أكثر بحركة الحيوانات.
If you think of a dolphin swimming or a cat running or jumping around,
إذا فكرت في دلفين يسبح أو قط يجري أو يقفز،
or even us as humans,
أو حتى نحن البشر،
when you go jogging or play tennis,
عندما تركض أو تلعب التنس،
we do amazing things.
نحن نقوم بأشياء عظيمة.
And in fact, our nervous system solves a very, very complex control problem.
وفي الحقيقة نظامنا العصبي يحل أكثر مشاكل التحكم تعقيدًا.
It has to coordinate more or less 200 muscles perfectly,
فهو يقوم بتنسيق حركة 200 عضلة بإتقان،
because if the coordination is bad, we fall over or we do bad locomotion.
لأنه إذا كان التنسيق سيئًا، سنسقط على الأرض أو تكون حركتنا سيئة.
And my goal is to understand how this works.
وهدفي هو معرفة كيف يعمل هذا النظام.
There are four main components behind animal locomotion.
هنالك 4 مكونات رئيسية لحركة الحيوانات.
The first component is just the body,
المكون الأول هو الجسد فقط،
and in fact we should never underestimate
وفي الحقيقة يجب أن لا نستهين
to what extent the biomechanics already simplify locomotion in animals.
بالمدى الذي بسطت فيه الكيمياء الحيوية الحركة في الحيوانات.
Then you have the spinal cord,
العنصر الثاني هو الحبل الشوكي
and in the spinal cord you find reflexes,
وفي الحبل الشوكي تجد ردود الفعل،
multiple reflexes that create a sensorimotor coordination loop
ردود الفعل المتعددة التي تخلق حلقة التنسيق الحسية
between neural activity in the spinal cord and mechanical activity.
بين النشاط العصبي في النخاع الشوكي والنشاط الميكانيكي.
A third component are central pattern generators.
المكون الثالث هو مولدات الأنماط المركزية.
These are very interesting circuits in the spinal cord of vertebrate animals
هذه دوائر موجودة في الحبل الشوكي في الحيوانات الفقارية
that can generate, by themselves,
يمكنها أن تولد بنفسها،
very coordinated rhythmic patterns of activity
أنماط إيقاعية متناسقة من النشاط
while receiving only very simple input signals.
عندما تستقبل إشارات إدخال بسيطة جدًا.
And these input signals
وهذه الإشارات
coming from descending modulation from higher parts of the brain,
تأتي بتناغم تنازلي من الأجزاء العليا للدماغ
like the motor cortex, the cerebellum, the basal ganglia,
مثل القشرة الدماغية المحركة و المخيخ والعقدة القاعدية
will all modulate activity of the spinal cord
مع نشاطات الحبل الشوكي
while we do locomotion.
حينما نقوم بالحركة.
But what's interesting is to what extent just a low-level component,
الشيء المثير للإهتمام هو المدى الذي أحدثه عنصر منخفض المستوى وهو
the spinal cord, together with the body,
الحبل الشوكي، مع الجسد،
already solve a big part of the locomotion problem.
يمكن أن يحل جزء كبيرا من مشكلة الحركة.
You probably know it by the fact that you can cut the head off a chicken,
أنتم في الأصل تعرفون ذلك تعرف حقيقة أنك إذا قطعت رأس دجاجة،
it can still run for a while,
يمكن للدجاجة أن تتحرك لفترة،
showing that just the lower part, spinal cord and body,
وهذا يثبت أن الجزء السفلي، الحبل الشوكي والجسم،
already solve a big part of locomotion.
يحلان جزءًا كبيرا من الحركة.
Now, understanding how this works is very complex,
والآن، فهم كيفية عمل ذلك معقد جدا،
because first of all,
لأنه أولا
recording activity in the spinal cord is very difficult.
تسجيل النشاط في الحبل الشوكي صعب جدا.
It's much easier to implant electrodes in the motor cortex
وضع أقطاب كهربائية في القشرة الدماغية المحركة أسهل بكثير
than in the spinal cord, because it's protected by the vertebrae.
من الحبل الشوكي لأنه محمي بالفقرات.
Especially in humans, very hard to do.
وخاصة بالنسبة للبشر، ذلك صعب جدا.
A second difficulty is that locomotion is really due to a very complex
وثانيا أنه بسبب أن الحركة هي نتاج تفاعل ديناميكي معقد جدا
and very dynamic interaction between these four components.
وتفاعل ديناميكي معقد جدا بين تلك العناصر الأربعة.
So it's very hard to find out what's the role of each over time.
لذا فإنه من الصعب جدا أن نكتشف أي دور يلعبه كل منها.
This is where biorobots like Pleurobot and mathematical models
وهنا يأتي دور الروبوتات الحيوية مثل بلوروبوت و النماذج الرياضية
can really help.
يمكن أن تساعد حقا.
So what's biorobotics?
ما هي الروبوتات الحيوية؟
Biorobotics is a very active field of research in robotics
الروبوتات الحيوية هو مجال ناشط في البحث في الروبوتات
where people want to take inspiration from animals
يستلهم فيه الناس من الحيوانات
to make robots to go outdoors,
لصنع روبوتات لتعمل خارجا
like service robots or search and rescue robots
مثل روبوتات الخدمة أو روبوتات البحث والإنقاذ
or field robots.
أو روبوتات الحقل.
And the big goal here is to take inspiration from animals
والهدف الكبير هنا أن نستلهم من الحيوانات
to make robots that can handle complex terrain --
لصنع روبوتات يمكنها تحمل تضاريس صعبة --
stairs, mountains, forests,
سلالم أو جبال أو غابات،
places where robots still have difficulties
أماكن تجدها الروبوتات صعبة
and where animals can do a much better job.
وتقوم فيها الحيوانات بعمل أفضل.
The robot can be a wonderful scientific tool as well.
يمكن للروبوت أن يكون أداة علمية رائعة أيضا.
There are some very nice projects where robots are used,
هناك بعض المشاريع الجيدة التي تُستخدم فيها الروبوتات
like a scientific tool for neuroscience, for biomechanics or for hydrodynamics.
كأداة علمية في علم الأعصاب أو الميكانيكا الحيوية أو الهيدروديناميك.
And this is exactly the purpose of Pleurobot.
وهذا بالضبط هدف بلوروبوت.
So what we do in my lab is to collaborate with neurobiologists
ما نقوم به في مختبري هو التعاون مع علماء الأعصاب
like Jean-Marie Cabelguen, a neurobiologist in Bordeaux in France,
مثل جين ماري كابلغون، عالم أعصاب في بوردكس في فرنسا،
and we want to make spinal cord models and validate them on robots.
ونريد أن نصنع نماذج للحبل الشوكي ونطبقها على الروبوتات.
And here we want to start simple.
وهنا نريد أن نبدأ ببساطة.
So it's good to start with simple animals
لهذا من الأفضل أن نبدأ بالحيوانات البسيطة
like lampreys, which are very primitive fish,
مثل الانقليس، وهو سمك بدائي جدا،
and then gradually go toward more complex locomotion,
ثم نتدرج إلى حركات معقدة أكثر،
like in salamanders,
مثل تلك بالنسبة للسلمندر،
but also in cats and in humans,
ولكن أيضا في القطط والبشر
in mammals.
في الثدييات.
And here, a robot becomes an interesting tool
وهنا، الروبوت أصبح أداة مثيرة للاهتمام
to validate our models.
لتطبيق نماذجنا.
And in fact, for me, Pleurobot is a kind of dream becoming true.
وفي الحقيقة، بليروبوت هو حلم تحول إلى واقع بالنسبة لي.
Like, more or less 20 years ago I was already working on a computer
قبل حوالي أقل أو أكثر من 20 سنة كنت فد بدأت بالعمل
making simulations of lamprey and salamander locomotion
لصنع محاكيات لحركة الانقليس والسلمندر على حاسوب
during my PhD.
خلال تحضيري للدكتوراه
But I always knew that my simulations were just approximations.
لكنني كنت دائما أعلم أن محاكياتي كانت فقط تقريبية.
Like, simulating the physics in water or with mud or with complex ground,
مثل، محاكاة الطبيعة في الماء أو مع الطين أو بيئة معقدة أكثر،
it's very hard to simulate that properly on a computer.
من الصعب محاكاة ذلك بطريقة صحيحة على حاسوب.
Why not have a real robot and real physics?
لم لا يكون روبوت حقيقي وطبيعة حقيقية؟
So among all these animals, one of my favorites is the salamander.
لذا من بين جميع هذه الحيوانات، المفضل بالنسبة لي هو السمندل.
You might ask why, and it's because as an amphibian,
ستتساءلون لماذا، لأنه حيوان برمائي،
it's a really key animal from an evolutionary point of view.
إنه فعلا حيوان مهمّ من نظرة تطورية.
It makes a wonderful link between swimming,
فهو يُشكل رابطا بين السباحة،
as you find it in eels or fish,
كما تجد ذلك في الثعابين أو السمك،
and quadruped locomotion, as you see in mammals, in cats and humans.
وذوات القوائم الأربعة، كما ترون ذلك في الثدييات
And in fact, the modern salamander
وفي واقع الأمر السمندل الحديث
is very close to the first terrestrial vertebrate,
قريب جدا للفقريات الأولية البرية،
so it's almost a living fossil,
إذن هي تقريبا احفوريات حية،
which gives us access to our ancestor,
ثتيح لنا الوصول إلى أسلافنا،
the ancestor to all terrestrial tetrapods.
أسلافنا من رباعيات الأرجل.
So the salamander swims
لذا يسبح السمندل
by doing what's called an anguilliform swimming gait,
بالقيام بما يُسمّى مشية السباحة الحلزونية،
so they propagate a nice traveling wave of muscle activity from head to tail.
لذا يقومون بنشر موجة نتيجة نشاطهم العضلي من الرأس إلى الذيل.
And if you place the salamander on the ground,
وإذا قمت بوضع السمندل على الأرض،
it switches to what's called a walking trot gait.
فسيُحوّل مشيته إلى ما يُسمّى مشية الهرولة.
In this case, you have nice periodic activation of the limbs
في هذه الحالة، لديكم نوع جميل من الحركة الدورية للأطراف
which are very nicely coordinated
وهي متناسقة بشكل رائع
with this standing wave undulation of the body,
مع موجة الجسم هذه،
and that's exactly the gait that you are seeing here on Pleurobot.
وهذابالضبط نوع المشية الذي ترونه هنا على بلوروبت.
Now, one thing which is very surprising and fascinating in fact
حاليا، شيء واحد رائع ومدهش حقا،
is the fact that all this can be generated just by the spinal cord and the body.
حقيقة أن كل هذا يمكن توليده فقط من خلال النخاع الشوكي والجسد.
So if you take a decerebrated salamander --
غن أخذنم سمندلا من دون وظيفة الدماغ --
it's not so nice but you remove the head --
هذا جميل ولكن ينبغي نزع الرأس--
and if you electrically stimulate the spinal cord,
وإن قمتم بتحفيز النخاع الشوكي كهربائيا،
at low level of stimulation this will induce a walking-like gait.
بمستوى منخفض للتحفيز هذا سيولد مشية تشبه المشية العادية.
If you stimulate a bit more, the gait accelerates.
وإن قمتم بالتحفيز أكثر، ستتارع المشية.
And at some point, there's a threshold,
وفي مكان ما، توجد عتبة،
and automatically, the animal switches to swimming.
وبصفة تلقائية سيتحول الحيوان إلى وضعية السباحة.
This is amazing.
هذا مدهش.
Just changing the global drive,
مجرد تغيير للتوجه الكلي،
as if you are pressing the gas pedal
كما لو أنك تضغط على دواسة البنزين
of descending modulation to your spinal cord,
لتعديل النخاع الشوكي،
makes a complete switch between two very different gaits.
وهو ما يُغيّر بين نوعين مختلفين من المشية.
And in fact, the same has been observed in cats.
في واقع الأمر، تمت ملاحظة نفس الشيء بالنسبة للقطط.
If you stimulate the spinal cord of a cat,
إذا قمت بتحفيز النخاع الشوكي لقطّ،
you can switch between walk, trot and gallop.
يمكن التغيير بين المشي والهرولة والركض.
Or in birds, you can make a bird switch between walking,
أما بالنسبة للطيور، يمكن أن يُغيّر الطير
at a low level of stimulation,
على مستوى منخفض من التحفيز،
and flapping its wings at high-level stimulation.
ويُرفرف أجنحته على مستوى عال من التخفيض.
And this really shows that the spinal cord
وهذا يُبرهن أن الحبل الشوكي
is a very sophisticated locomotion controller.
متحكّم متطور جدا في الحركة.
So we studied salamander locomotion in more detail,
لذا درسنا حركة السمندل بشكل مفصل أكثر،
and we had in fact access to a very nice X-ray video machine
واستطعنا الحصول على آلة للفيديو بالأشعة السينية
from Professor Martin Fischer in Jena University in Germany.
من الدكتور مارتن فيشر في جامعة جينا في ألمانيا.
And thanks to that, you really have an amazing machine
وبفضل هذا، لدينا آلة مذهلة
to record all the bone motion in great detail.
لتسجيل جميع حركات العظم بكلّ التفاصيل.
That's what we did.
وهذا ما قمنا به.
So we basically figured out which bones are important for us
لذا حددنا العظام المهمّة بالنسبة لنا
and collected their motion in 3D.
وجمعنا حركاتهم بطريقة 3D.
And what we did is collect a whole database of motions,
وما قمنا به هو جمع قاعدة بيانات كاملة من الحركات،
both on ground and in water,
على الأرض وفي الماء،
to really collect a whole database of motor behaviors
لجمع قاعدة بيانات للحركات
that a real animal can do.
يمكن لحيوان القيام بها.
And then our job as roboticists was to replicate that in our robot.
ويكمن دورنا كمختصين في الروبوتات لتشخيص هذا في روبوتنا.
So we did a whole optimization process to find out the right structure,
لذا قمنا بعملية تحسين كلية لإيجاد الهيكل الصحيح،
where to place the motors, how to connect them together,
لوضع المحركات، وكيفية ربطها معا،
to be able to replay these motions as well as possible.
والقدرة على إعادة هذه الحركات قدر الإمكان.
And this is how Pleurobot came to life.
وهكذا أصبح البلوروبوت حيّا.
So let's look at how close it is to the real animal.
لذا لنرى مدى الشبه بينه وبين الحيوان الحقيقي.
So what you see here is almost a direct comparison
لذل ما ترونه هنا هو تقريبا مقارنة مباشرة
between the walking of the real animal and the Pleurobot.
بين مشية الحيوان الحقيقي والبلوروبوت.
You can see that we have almost a one-to-one exact replay
كما ترون تقريبا يقع التكرار
of the walking gait.
للمشية بالضبط.
If you go backwards and slowly, you see it even better.
إذا رجعت إلى الخلف قليلا، يمكنك رؤية ذلك بطريقة أفضل.
But even better, we can do swimming.
ولكن أحسن من ذلك، يمكننا السباحة.
So for that we have a dry suit that we put all over the robot --
لذا من أجل ذلك، نملك بدلة جافة نغطي بها الروبوت--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and then we can go in water and start replaying the swimming gaits.
ثم نستطيع وضعه في الماء والبدء في المشي.
And here, we were very happy, because this is difficult to do.
وهنا كنا سعداء، لأن هذا يصعب القيام به.
The physics of interaction are complex.
إن فيزياء التفاعل معقدة جدا.
Our robot is much bigger than a small animal,
فروبوتنا أكبر بكثير من حيوان صغير،
so we had to do what's called dynamic scaling of the frequencies
لذا كان علينا القيام بما يُسمّى التدريج الديناميكي للترددات
to make sure we had the same interaction physics.
للتأكد من نفس التفاعل الفيزيائي.
But you see at the end, we have a very close match,
ولكن كما ترون في النهاية لدينا تقريبا نفس النموذج،
and we were very, very happy with this.
وكنا مسرورين بذلك جدا.
So let's go to the spinal cord.
لذا لنتحدث عن النخاع الشوكي.
So here what we did with Jean-Marie Cabelguen
لذا هذا ما قمنا به مع جون ماري كابلجون
is model the spinal cord circuits.
تصميم نموذج دوائر الحبل الشوكي.
And what's interesting is that the salamander
والمثير للإهتمام أن السمندل
has kept a very primitive circuit,
حافظ على دارة بدائية جدا،
which is very similar to the one we find in the lamprey,
وهي مشابهة تماما لما وجدناه عند الانقليس،
this primitive eel-like fish,
هذا ثعبان البحر البدائي المشابه للسمكة،
and it looks like during evolution,
ويبدو أنه خلال التطور،
new neural oscillators have been added to control the limbs,
أُضيفت مذبذبات عصبية للتحكم في الأطراف
to do the leg locomotion.
للقيام بتحريك الساق.
And we know where these neural oscillators are
ونعرف أين توجد هذه المذبذبات العصبية
but what we did was to make a mathematical model
ولكن ما قمنا به كان صنع نموذج رياضي
to see how they should be coupled
لنرى كيف ينبغي أن ترتبط
to allow this transition between the two very different gaits.
للسماح بهذا التغيير بين نوعين مختلفين من المشيات.
And we tested that on board of a robot.
وقمنا باختبار ذلك على الروبوت.
And this is how it looks.
وهذا ما يبدو عليه الأمر.
So what you see here is a previous version of Pleurobot
لذا ما ترونه هنا هو نسخة سابقة لبلوروبوت
that's completely controlled by our spinal cord model
يتم التحكم فيه من خلال نموذجنا للنخاع الشوكي
programmed on board of the robot.
المبرمج على الروبوت.
And the only thing we do
الشيء الوحيد الذي نقوم به
is send to the robot through a remote control
هو إرسال إشارتين من خلال أداة التحكم
the two descending signals it normally should receive
والتي من المفترض استقبالها
from the upper part of the brain.
من الجزء العلوي للدماغ.
And what's interesting is, by playing with these signals,
والمثير للاهتمام، أنه من خلال اللعب بهذه الإشارات،
we can completely control speed, heading and type of gait.
يمكننا التحكم بالسرعة والاتجاه ونوع المشية بشكل كلي.
For instance,
على سبيل المثال،
when we stimulate at a low level, we have the walking gait,
عندما نقوم بالتحفيز على مستوى منخفض، نتحصل على المشي،
and at some point, if we stimulate a lot,
وفي مرحلة ما، إذا قمنا بالكثير من التحفيز،
very rapidly it switches to the swimming gait.
تتحوّل المشية بسرعة كبيرة إلى السباحة.
And finally, we can also do turning very nicely
وأخيرا، يمكننا تغيير الاتجاه بكل سهولة وروعة
by just stimulating more one side of the spinal cord than the other.
من خلال تحفيز جانب واحد من النخاع الشوكي.
And I think it's really beautiful
أعتقد أن ذلك جميل كيف قامت الطبيعة
how nature has distributed control
بتوزيع التحكم
to really give a lot of responsibility to the spinal cord
لإعطاء النخاع الشوكي المسؤولية الكبيرة
so that the upper part of the brain doesn't need to worry about every muscle.
لكي لا يحتاج الجزء العلوي من الدماغ إلى القلق على كل عضلة.
It just has to worry about this high-level modulation,
ينبغي أن يتحكم في الحركات الصعبة،
and it's really the job of the spinal cord to coordinate all the muscles.
وتكمن وظيفة النخاع الشوكي في التنسيق بين جميع العضلات.
So now let's go to cat locomotion and the importance of biomechanics.
الآن لننطلق إلى تحرك القط وأهمية الميكانيكا الحيوية.
So this is another project
إذن هذا مشروع آخر
where we studied cat biomechanics,
حيث درسنا الميكانيكا الحيوية للقطط،
and we wanted to see how much the morphology helps locomotion.
وأردنا معرفة مدى مساعدة الشكل على الحركة.
And we found three important criteria in the properties,
ووجدنا 3 أشياء مهمة للخاصيات،
basically, of the limbs.
أساسية للأطراف.
The first one is that a cat limb
أول شيء هو أن أطراف القط
more or less looks like a pantograph-like structure.
تشبه هيكلتها البنتوغراف.
So a pantograph is a mechanical structure
البنتوغراف هو هيكل ميكانيكي
which keeps the upper segment and the lower segments always parallel.
يُحافظ على الجزء العلوي والسفلي دائما متوازين.
So a simple geometrical system that kind of coordinates a bit
إذا نظام هندسي بسيط يُنسّق نوعا ما
the internal movement of the segments.
الحركة الداخلية للأجزاء.
A second property of cat limbs is that they are very lightweight.
والخاصيّة الأخرى لأطراف القط أنها خفيفة الوزن.
Most of the muscles are in the trunk,
توجد معظم العضلات في الجسم،
which is a good idea, because then the limbs have low inertia
وهذه فكرة جيدة، لأن الأطراف لها قصور ذاتي ضئيل
and can be moved very rapidly.
ويمكن أن تتحرك بسرعة كبيرة جدا.
The last final important property is this very elastic behavior of the cat limb,
والخاصية الأخيرة المهمّة هي السلوك المرن جدا لأطراف القط،
so to handle impacts and forces.
للتعامل مع الآثار والقُوى.
And this is how we designed Cheetah-Cub.
وهكذا قمنا بتصميم شبل الفهد.
So let's invite Cheetah-Cub onstage.
لندعو شبل الفهد إلى المسرح.
So this is Peter Eckert, who does his PhD on this robot,
هذا السيد بيتر إكرت الذي يقوم بالكتوراه خاصته حول هذا الروبوت،
and as you see, it's a cute little robot.
وكما ترون، هو روبوت صغير جميل.
It looks a bit like a toy,
يبدو مثل اللعبة،
but it was really used as a scientific tool
ولكن تم استعماله حقا كأداة علمية
to investigate these properties of the legs of the cat.
للتحقيق في هذه الخاصيات لأطراف القط.
So you see, it's very compliant, very lightweight,
ذا كما ترون، هي متوافقة للغاية، وخفيفة الوزن،
and also very elastic,
ومرنة جدا أيضا،
so you can easily press it down and it will not break.
لذا يمكنكم الضغط عليها ولن يتم كسرها.
It will just jump, in fact.
بل ستقفز في الحقيقة.
And this very elastic property is also very important.
وخاصية المرونة هذه مهمة جدا.
And you also see a bit these properties
ترون قليلا من هذه الخاصيات
of these three segments of the leg as pantograph.
لهذه الأجزاء الثلاثة للساق كبنتوغراف.
Now, what's interesting is that this quite dynamic gait
حاليا، المثير للاهتمام هو هذه المشية الديناميكية
is obtained purely in open loop,
هي نتيجة لوثبة كبيرة،
meaning no sensors, no complex feedback loops.
يعني دون أجهزة استشعار ولا ردود فعل معقدة للوثبات.
And that's interesting, because it means
وهذا مثير للاهتمام لأنه يعني
that just the mechanics already stabilized this quite rapid gait,
أن الميكانكيون هم من ثبتوا هذه المشية السريعة جدا،
and that really good mechanics already basically simplify locomotion.
وأن الميكانكيون الماهرون فقط هم من يستطيعون تلخيص الحركة.
To the extent that we can even disturb a bit locomotion,
يمكننا حتى تعديل الحركة،
as you will see in the next video,
كما سترون في الفيديو التالي،
where we can for instance do some exercise where we have the robot go down a step,
أين يمكننا القيام ببعض التمارين حيث ينبغي على الروبوت أن ينخفض،
and the robot will not fall over,
ولن يسقط،
which was a surprise for us.
والتي كانت مفاجأة بالنسبة لنا.
This is a small perturbation.
هذا تعديل بسيط.
I was expecting the robot to immediately fall over,
كنت أتوقع السقوط الفوري للروبوت،
because there are no sensors, no fast feedback loop.
بسبب انعدام أجهزة الاستشعار وردود الفعل السريعة.
But no, just the mechanics stabilized the gait,
ولكن لا، قام الميكانيكيون بتثبيت الحركة فقط،
and the robot doesn't fall over.
والروبوت لم يسقط.
Obviously, if you make the step bigger, and if you have obstacles,
من الواضح، إذا كانت الخطوة أكبر ومع وجود عديد العقبات،
you need the full control loops and reflexes and everything.
تحتاج إلى التحكم الكلي في الوثبات وردود الفعل وكل شيء.
But what's important here is that just for small perturbation,
ولكن المهم هنا لمجرد اضطراب صغير،
the mechanics are right.
الميكانيكيون هم على صواب.
And I think this is a very important message
وأعتقد أن هذه رسالة مهمة للغاية
from biomechanics and robotics to neuroscience,
الميكانيكا الحيوية والروبوتات إلى علم الأعصاب
saying don't underestimate to what extent the body already helps locomotion.
والتي تشير إلى عدم التقليل من شأن الجسم المساعد على الحركة.
Now, how does this relate to human locomotion?
والآن، كيف يرتبط هذا بالحركة الإنسانية؟
Clearly, human locomotion is more complex than cat and salamander locomotion,
من الواضح أن الحركة الإنسانية أكثر تعقيدا من حركة القطط والسمندل،
but at the same time, the nervous system of humans is very similar
ولكن في نفس الوقت، الجهاز العصبي الإنساني مشابه
to that of other vertebrates.
للفقريات الأخرى.
And especially the spinal cord
وخاصة النخاع الشوكي
is also the key controller for locomotion in humans.
وهو مفتاح التحكم للحركة عند الإنسان.
That's why, if there's a lesion of the spinal cord,
لذلك، عند وجود ضرر في مستوى النخاع الشوكي،
this has dramatic effects.
تكون تأثيراته خطيرة.
The person can become paraplegic or tetraplegic.
يمكن أن يُصاب الإنسان بشلل سفلي أو شلل كلّي.
This is because the brain loses this communication
وهذا بشبب فقدان الدماغ التواصل
with the spinal cord.
مع النخاع الشوكي.
Especially, it loses this descending modulation
يفقد خاصّة هذا التعديل للحركة
to initiate and modulate locomotion.
لبدء الحركة وتعديلها.
So a big goal of neuroprosthetics
لذا الهدف بالنسبة للجهاز العصبي
is to be able to reactivate that communication
هو إعادة تفعيل هذا التواصل
using electrical or chemical stimulations.
باستخدام التحفيز الكهربائي والكيميائي.
And there are several teams in the world that do exactly that,
وتوجد العديد من المجموعات في العالم تقوم بالمثل،
especially at EPFL.
خاصة EPFL.
My colleagues Grégoire Courtine and Silvestro Micera,
زملائي غريغوار كورتين وسيلفسترو ميسارا،
with whom I collaborate.
الذين عملت معهما.
But to do this properly, it's very important to understand
ولكن للقيام بهذا بصورة صحيحة، من المهم أن تفهم
how the spinal cord works,
كيفية اشتغال النخاع الشوكي،
how it interacts with the body,
كيفية تفاعله مع الجسم،
and how the brain communicates with the spinal cord.
وطريقة التواصل بين الدماغ والنخاع الشوكي.
This is where the robots and models that I've presented today
وهنا سيلعب الروبوتات والنماذج التي قدمتها اليوم
will hopefully play a key role
دورا أساسيا
towards these very important goals.
لتحقيق هذه الأهداف المهمة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Auke, I've seen in your lab other robots
برونو خيوساني: أوك، لقد رأيت في مختبرك روبوتات أخرى
that do things like swim in pollution
التي تقوم بأشياء مثل السباحة في مكان ملوث
and measure the pollution while they swim.
ويقيسون مدى التلوث بينما يسبحون.
But for this one,
ولكن بالنسبة لهذا،
you mentioned in your talk, like a side project,
لقد ذكرت في حديثك كمشروع ثانوي،
search and rescue,
البحث والإنقاذ،
and it does have a camera on its nose.
ولدى الروبوت كاميرا على مستوى أنفه.
Auke Ijspeert: Absolutely. So the robot --
أوك اسبجرت: بالطبع. إذن الروبوت --
We have some spin-off projects
لدينا بعض المشاريع الجانبية
where we would like to use the robots to do search and rescue inspection,
حيث نريد استخدام الروبوتات للقيام بالبحوث والإنقاذ،
so this robot is now seeing you.
إذن الروبوت الآن يراك.
And the big dream is to, if you have a difficult situation
والحلم الكبير هو، إذا واجهت وضعية صعبة
like a collapsed building or a building that is flooded,
كانهيار مبنى أو مبنى غمرته الفيضانات،
and this is very dangerous for a rescue team or even rescue dogs,
وهذا خطير جدا لفريق الإنقاذ أو حتى كلاب الإنقاذ،
why not send in a robot that can crawl around, swim, walk,
لما لا يتمّ بعث روبوت يمكنه الزحف والسباحة والمشي،
with a camera onboard to do inspection and identify survivors
مرفوق بكاميرا للقيام بالتفتيش وتعقّب الناجين
and possibly create a communication link with the survivor.
ومن المحتمل خلق نوع من الاتصال مع الناجين.
BG: Of course, assuming the survivors don't get scared by the shape of this.
برونو خيوساني: طبعا، على افتراض أن لا يخاف الناجون من شكله
AI: Yeah, we should probably change the appearance quite a bit,
أوك: نعم، ربما ينبغي حتما أن نُغيّر المظهر قليلا
because here I guess a survivor might die of a heart attack
لأنني اعتقد أنه ربما يموت الناجي بسكتة قلبية
just of being worried that this would feed on you.
خوفا من أن يتم التهامه من قبل هذا الروبوت.
But by changing the appearance and it making it more robust,
ولكن مع تغيير المظهر وجعله أكثر قوة،
I'm sure we can make a good tool out of it.
أنا متأكد أنه يمكننا أن نصنع آلة جيدة منه.
BG: Thank you very much. Thank you and your team.
برونو خيوساني: شكرا لكم كثيرا. شكرا لكم ولفريقكم.